The Papers of James Hoge Ricks 1916-1956
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
The Papers of James Hoge Ricks 1916-1956
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 85-14
This collections consists of 13 boxes.
The James Hoge Ricks Papers, 1916-1956, consist of 13 boxes of selected correspondence and records of the first judge of the Richmond Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
A native of Caroline County and a life-long Quaker, James Hoge Ricks (1886-1958) studied at Guilford College in North Carolina (A.B, 1905) and T. C. Williams School of Law at the University of Richmond (LL.B., 1908). He was admitted to the Bar in 1909 and became clerk and parole officer of the Juvenile Division of Police Court in 1912.
In 1916, Ricks became a judge of the new court at age twenty-nine and held the position until his retirement in 1956. The juvenile court movement was an outgrowth of the Progressive era, and throughout his life, Judge Ricks remained active in various social movements spawned by "humanitarian progressives" and the National Conference of Social Work (prior to 1917, the National Conference of Charities and Corrections).
Ricks was a founder and vice-president of the National Conference of Juvenile Court Judges, an organizer and officer of the Richmond Community Fund, and twice president of the National Probation Association.
Scope and Content Information
The Ricks Papers, 1916-1956, consist of 4 shelf feet of selected correspondence and records of the first judge of the Richmond Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court. This collection of correspondence files and materials selected from the much larger main files of the court by graduate student George B. Curtis. In accordance with state law requiring confidentiality of case records, all case materials have been separated and returned to the court.
Contents List
- [Biographical and Legal Notes] 1974, n.d. (Box 1)
- Addresses 1924-1940, n.d. (Box 1)
- Addresses and Historical Material 1930-1945 (Box 1)
- Articles by Ricks 1928 (Box 1)
- American Birth Control League 1925-1938 (Box 1)
- Bootblacks 1938-1926 (Box 1)
- Cadet Corps 1929-1935 (Box 1)
- Capital Punishment 1921-1935 (Box 1)
- Charles T. Booth (Charity Fund) 1936-1944 (Box 1)
- Boys Club 1925-1933 (Box 1)
- Child Welfare League of America 1925-1937 (Box 1)
- Child Welfare Conference n.d. (Box 1)
- Children's Memorial Clinic 1938-1942 (Box 1)
- City Charter Commission of Richmond 1947 (Box 1)
- Civil Justices Court 1926, 1934 (Box 1)
- Clippings 1927, 1941-1946 (Box 1)
- Colored Playgrounds Recreation Association 1925-1946 (Box 1)
- Committee on Militarism in Education 1925-[1934?] (Box 2)
- Community Council of Richmond 1940-1948 (Box 2)
- Community Fund of Richmond 1943-1946 (Box 2)
- Confidentiality of Records 1944 (Box 2)
- Court-Miscellaneous 1944-1945 (Box 2)
- Crimes-Causes and Effects 1936-1940 (Box 2)
- F. Lawton Crutchfield 1932-1936 (Box 2)
- Judge John A. Crutchfield 1930 (Box 2)
- Department of Justice-John W. Andrews 1946-1947 (Box 2)
- Detention Home 1927-1938 (Box 2)
- Desarmament-Vinson Bill 1934 (Box 2)
- FBI-J. Edgar Hoover 1939-1940 (Box 2)
- Friends Association of Colored Children 1944-1948 (Box 2)
- Girl Scouts of Richmond 1938-1943 (Box 2)
- Governor's Conference on Child Labor 1927-1935 (Box 2)
- Greek American Association 1923 (Box 2)
- Interracial Commission 1929-1939 (Box 2)
- Juvenile Court Anniversary 1941 (Box 2)
- Juvenile Court Charity Fund 1929-1946 (Box 3)
- Juvenile Court Committee-Virginia Conference of Social Work 1948-1950 (Box 3)
- Juvenile Court Memoranda 1942-1944 (Box 3)
- Juvenile Court-Photos, Building Plan n.d. (Box 3)
- Juvenile Court Rules 1932-1945 (Box 3)
- Juvenile & Domestic Relations Court Judges 1932-1945 (Box 3)
- Juvenile Court Survey 1941 (Box 3)
- Law and Court Decisions 1919-1950, n.d., 2 folders (Box 3)
- Mayor's Advisory Committee Survey on Juvenile Court 1940-1944 (Box 4)
- National Association of Juvenile Court Judges 1936-1953 (Box 4)
- Norfolk Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court 1926-1946 (Box 4)
- Refresher Course-Juvenile Court Judges 1946 (Box 4)
- Roanoke-Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court 1937-1948 (Box 4)
- Survey-Juvenile and Domestic Relations Court ca. 1925, 1926 (Box 4)
- Virginia Council of Juvenile Court Judges 1945-1951, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Juvenile Courts 1936-1945 (Box 4)
- Juvenile Delinquency Conference 1946 (Box 5)
- Juvenile Protective Association 1926 (Box 5)
- A.S. Macfarlane 1929-1938 (Box 5)
- Maryland Industrial Training School for Boys 1923 (Box 5)
- Re: Joseph T. Martin Dinner ca. 1933 (Box 5)
- Mellon Foundation 1949-1952 (Box 5)
- Joe Mickens Case 1941-1942 (Box 5)
- Re: Mothers' Pension 1927-1936 (Box 5)
- National Child Labor Law 1925-1935 (Box 5)
- National Children's Bureau 1930-1944 (Box 5)
- National Committee for Mental Hygiene 1921-1942 (Box 5)
- National Conference of Social Work 1932-1947 (Box 5)
- National Conference on Prevention of Juvenile Delinquency 1946 (Box 5)
- National Council for the Prevention of War 1947-1950 (Box 5)
- National Crime Commission 1927-1932 (Box 5)
- National Probation Association 1930-1948
- Re: NRA Newspapers Publishers' Codes 1933 (Box 6)
- Navy Recruiting 1932-1940 (Box 6)
- Negro Crime Commission 1941 (Box 6)
- Negro Welfare Survey 1928-1937 (Box 6)
- New Legislation 1924-1948 (Box 6)
- New York School of Social Work 1925-1933 (Box 6)
- Paternity Legislation 1919-1941 (Box 6)
- Police Women-Washington 1926-1928 (Box 6)
- Probation and Parole 1938-1942 (Box 6)
- Probation Bill-Federal 1934-1941 (Box 6)
- Re: Prohibition and Liquor Control Law 1929-1937 (Box 6)
- Racial Integrity Law and Indians 1930 (Box 6)
- Richmond Bar Association 1937-1948 (Box 6)
- Richmond City Attorney 1933-1948 (Box 6)
- Richmond City Council Finance Committee 1932-1948 (Box 6)
- Richmond City Public Schools 1935-1947 (Box 7)
- Franklin D. Roosevelt 1933-1935 (Box 7)
- Runaways 1943 (Box 7)
- Shrubbery Hill Parental School 1925-1927 (Box 7)
- Social Services Bureau 1941-1944 (Box 7)
- Trial Justices Association 1934-1945 (Box 7)
- Virginia Advisory Council 1935, 1945, 1949 (Box 7)
- Virginia Conference of Social Work 1926-1947 (Box 7)
- Virginia Governors-Price, Peery, Pollard 1932-1941 (Box 7)
- Virginia Governors-Darden and Tuck 1942-1948 (Box 7)
- Virginia League for Planned Parenthood 1947 (Box 7)
- Virginia State Bar Association 1930-1945 (Box 7)
- Visitors 1940 (Box 7)
- United Nations 1948-1949 (Box 7)
- WPA-General Correspondence 1939-1941 (Box 7)
- WPA- Probation Project 1937-1939 (Box 7)
- Orville Lee Whetzel 1946 (Box 7)
- YMCA & YWCA, Richmond, Virginia 1945-1948 (Box 7)
- Miscellany 1936-1947 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous Pamphlets 1911-1942 (Box 7)
- Applications-Deputy Clerk 1930-1947 (Box 8)
- Applications-Miscellaneous Positions 1943-1948 (Box 8)
- Applications-Referee 1944-1946 (Box 8)
- Applications-Miscellaneous ca. 1944-1946 (Box 8)
- Applications-Chief Probation Officer 1947 (Box 8)
- Applications-Intake Officer 1943-1945 (Box 8)
- Applications Chief Probation Officer; Supt. of Detention Home 1943-1945 (Box 8)
- Applications-Counselor for Negro Children 1943-1945 (Box 8)
- Applications-Colored 1941-1943 (Box 8)
- Applications 1940-1945 (Box 9)
- ABC Board 1934-1948 (Box 9)
- Air Rifles and Guns 1927-1934 (Box 9)
- Boarding Houses for Children 1921-1933 (Box 9)
- Bethany Home 1935-1936 (Box 9)
- Boy Scouts of America 1924-1925 (Box 9)
- Boys' Home-Covington, Virginia 1936-1944 (Box 9)
- Bank Statements 1931-1954 (Box 9)
- Children's Home 1940-1944 (Box 9)
- Central Application Bureau 1939 (Box 9)
- Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Company 1943 (Box 9)
- Children's Aid Society of Richmond 1940-1944 (Box 9)
- Church and Social Service Worker 1937 (Box 9)
- Council on Social Workers 1925-1935 (Box 9)
- Crime Prevention Bureau of Richmond 1937-1947 (Box 9)
- Directories-Social Workers, Probation Officers 1926-1937 (Box 9)
- Detention Home Rules 1934-1953 (Box 9)
- Detention Home-Staff and Advisory Committee 1940-1953 (Box 9)
- Detention Home-Medical Reports 1941-1954 (Box 9)
- Detention Home Repairs 1940-1948 (Box 10)
- Detention Home-Application for Assistant Matrons, Medical Inspector 1931-1947 (Box 10)
- Driver Permits 1927-1946 (Box 10)
- Estimates 1939-1942 (Box 10)
- Extradition ca. 1936-1940 (Box 10)
- Mrs. F. H. Fishburne (Charity Fund) 1937-1938 (Box 10)
- Family Service Society 1942-1947 (Box 10)
- Hanover Industrial School 1945-1948 (Box 10)
- Home Owners' Loan Corporation 1933-1934 (Box 10)
- J. M. Hord 1932-1937 (Box 10)
- W. T. Jones 1933-1941 (Box 10)
- Juvenile Court Insurance 1926-1946 (Box 10)
- Juvenile Court-Automobiles 1929, 1953 (Box 11)
- Juvenile Court Staff-Payroll 1927-1946 (Box 11)
- Magistrates 1939-1944 (Box 11)
- Manassas Industrial School 1935 (Box 11)
- Marriage Counseling Service 1948-1952 (Box 11)
- Medical Society of Virginia 1934-1945 (Box 11)
- Memorial Guidance Clinic 1947-1948 (Box 11)
- Memorial Home for Girls 1937-1944 (Box 11)
- Carroll R. Minor 1936-1937 (Box 11)
- Norfolk Community Fund 1934 (Box 11)
- National Youth Organization 1936-1943 (Box 11)
- Organization of Social Forces 1937 (Box 11)
- Parents' Council 1928 (Box 11)
- Parental School 1930-1931 (Box 11)
- Pensions 1942-1944 (Box 11)
- Prisoners of Aid Association 1930-1931 (Box 11)
- Probation Officers-Application and Requests 1939-1946 (Box 11)
- Public Welfare 1927-1941 (Box 11)
- Ration Books 1943 (Box 11)
- Reading Lists n.d. (Box 11)
- Miscellaneous Receipts 1944-1946 (Box 11)
- Records and Statistics 1924, n.d. (Box 11)
- Requistions 1941-1943 (Box 12)
- Retirement System 1944-1945 (Box 12)
- Richmond Building Inspector 1934-1945 (Box 12)
- Richmond Chief of Police 1943-1948 (Box 12)
- Richmond City Comptroller 1931-1946 (Box 12)
- Richmond City Home 1944 (Box 12)
- Richmond City Council 1931-1948 (Box 12)
- Richmond Commonwealth's Attorney 1942-1944 (Box 12)
- Richmond Council of Churches 1925 (Box 12)
- Richmond Council of Social Agencies 1925-1946 (Box 12)
- Richmond Curfew Ordinance 1923-1944 (Box 12)
- Richmond Employment Bureau 1934 (Box 12)
- Richmond First Club 1953-1954 (Box 12)
- Richmond Home for Boys 1937, 1946 (Box 12)
- Richmond Mayors 1942-1948 (Box 12)
- Richmond Ordinances 1934-1948 (Box 12)
- Richmond Parks and Playgrounds 1931-1941 (Box 12)
- Richmond Public Safety 1941-1945 (Box 13)
- Richmond Public Works 1933-1948 (Box 13)
- Richmond Social Service Bureau 1941-1944 (Box 13)
- Russell Sage Foundation 1925 (Box 13)
- St. Mary's Industrial School 1925-1931 (Box 13)
- Salaries-Court Officers 1922-1923 (Box 13)
- Salem Baptist Orphanage 1937 (Box 13)
- Salvation Army 1925 (Box 13)
- School Attendance Officer-Richmond 1944-1947 (Box 13)
- Social Service Exchange 1926-1949 (Box 13)
- State Federation of Colored Women's Clubs 1936 (Box 13)
- Stockdon, W.I. Jr. 1925-1944 (Box 13)
- Superintendent of Documents 1935 (Box 13)
- Travelers Aid Society 1933-1943 (Box 13)
- Trial Justices-Counties and Cities 1937-ca. 1940 (Box 13)
- Unemployment ca. 1932 (Box 13)
- U.S. Federation of Justice 1928-1930 (Box 13)
- Venereal Disease Control 1945 (Box 13)
- Virginia Conference Orphanage 1940-1943 (Box 13)
- Virginia-Attorney General 1931-1947 (Box 13)
- Virginia-Auditor 1942 (Box 13)
- Virginia-Commissioner of Labor 1932-1947 (Box 13)
- Virginia-Comptroller 1939-1943 (Box 13)
- Virginia-Department of Public Welfare 1944-1948 (Box 13)
- Virginia-Penitentiary 1936-1942 (Box 13)
- Virginia-Unemployment Compensation Commission 1937-1938 (Box 13)
- Virginia-Western State Hospital 1935 (Box 13)
- Virginia-Welfare Council 1935-1946 (Box 13)
- Visiting Teachers 1932-1933 (Box 13)
- War Memorial 1953-1954 (Box 13)
- William Byrd Community House 1928-1944 (Box 13)
- William and Mary College-Richmond Division 1929-1946 (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous 1920-1949, 3 folders (Box 13)